Every time we made contact with them, we kept serving them food, day after day, so we needed to grow. We moved into the big coliseum. 25,000 meals became 50,000 meals, became, all of a sudden, the biggest restaurant in the world. We were making close to 70,000 meals a day from one location alone. (Applause) Volunteers began showing up by the hundreds. At one point, we got more than 7,000 volunteers that were at least one hour or more with us, at any given moment, more than 700 people at once. You saw that we began creating a movement, a movement that had a very simple idea everybody could rally behind: let's feed the hungry. And we began making food that people could recognize, not things that come from a faraway place in plastic bags that you open and you cannot even smell. (Laughter) We began making the foods that people feel home. People in these moments, they had this urgency of feeling they are alive, that somebody cares. One meal at a time, it didn't only become something used to bring calories to their bodies, calories that they needed, but they needed something else. They wanted to make sure that you and you and you and you, that you were caring, that we were sending the message that we are with you. Give us time, we are trying to fix this. That's what we found every time we began joining the communities. Fresh fruit began coming, even when in FEMA, they were asking me, "José, how are you able to get the food?" Simple: by calling and paying and getting. (Laughter) (Applause) We began feeding people in San Juan. Before you knew, we were feeding the 78 municipalities all across the island. We needed a plan. One kitchen alone was not going to feed the island. I went to FEMA. They kicked me out with eight armored guards and AK-47s. I told them, "I want 18 kitchens around the island." Guess what? Three days ago, we reached our 18th kitchen around Puerto Rico. (Applause) People began being fed. Volunteers kept showing up. We never had any system to deliver the food, people would tell me. Sure, we had the system. The entire island of Puerto Rico was the perfect delivery system. Anybody with a truck wanted to help. Anybody going from A to B was for us the way to be bringing hope and a plate and a whole meal to anybody. We began finding amazing systems to do these food trucks, 10 amazing food trucks. We began learning not to use the place that needed the food, but the number, the number of the apartment: Lolo, a 92-year-old veteran that was surrounded by water. We began giving not only hope to people, but knowing their names, checking day after day, making sure that those elderly people will never, ever again feel alone in a moment of disrepair. And we began going to the deeper areas, places that all of a sudden, the bridges were broken, but we had to go, because it was easy to stay in San Juan. We had to go to those places that actually, they really needed us. And we kept going, and people kept waiting for us, because they knew that we will always show up, because we will never leave them alone. (Applause) The food trucks became our angels, and the food trucks kept sending hope, but we saw we needed more: Vieques and Culebra, two islands far away from the island -- somebody had to be feeding them. We didn't only bring food and make a hotel kitchen operation in Vieques and bring daily food to Culebra. We brought the first water purification system to the island of Vieques, where we could be filtering one gallon per minute. All of a sudden, big problems become very simple, low-hanging fruit solutions, only by doing, not planning and meeting in a very big building. (Laughter) And then we found creative ways. We needed helicopters. We asked. We got. We needed planes. We asked, we paid, and we got. We kept sending food to those places that really were in need. And the simple ideas just become powerful. Volunteers will go to the edges of the island. All of a sudden, it was a movement. The teams of World Central Kitchen will be received with prayers, with songs, with claps, with hugs, with smiles. We were able to connect in so many corners. When I tell you that even the National Guard began calling us because our national poor guy's guards, big heroes in a moment of chaos, they couldn't get a simple humble plate of hot food. And partnerships show up. Mercy Corps, HSI from Homeland Security, partnerships that they didn't happen calling the top. They happened in the hotel room, in the middle of the street, in the middle of the mountains. We saw that by working together, we can even reach more people. Partnerships that happen by logic, and the urgency of now is put to the service of the people. When we have emergency relief organizations, we cannot be planning about how to give aid a month from now. We have to be ready to start giving help the second after something happens. And children were fed, and all of a sudden, the island, while still in a very special moment where everything is fragile, we saw that an NGO like ours -- we didn't want to break the private sector -- that already, small restaurants were being opened, that somehow, normalcy, whatever normalcy means today in Puerto Rico, was happening. We began trying to be sending the message: we need to start moving away from the places that are already stabilized and keep concentrating in the areas that really need help. (Video): People of Puerto Rico, two million meals! José Andrés OK, let me translate this to you. (Laughter) Almost 28 days later, more than 10 food trucks, more than 7,000 volunteers, 18 kitchens ... we served more than two million meals. (Applause) (Applause ends) And you guys coming here to TED, you should be proud, because we know many of you, you are part of the change. But the change is only going to happen if after we leave this amazing conference, we put the amazing ideas and inspiration that we get, and we believe that nothing is impossible, and we put our know-how to the service of those in need. I arrived to an island trying to feed a few people, and I saw a big problem, and all of a sudden, the people of Puerto Rico saw the same problem as me, and only we did one thing: we began cooking. And so the people of Puerto Rico and the chefs of Puerto Rico, in a moment of disrepair, began bringing hope, not by meeting, not by planning, but with only one simple idea: let's start cooking and let's start feeding the people of Puerto Rico. Thank you. (Applause) Dave Troy: Go back out. (Laughter) DT: The public loves you. (Applause) Nate Mook: A couple of quick questions, because I think some folks would be interested to hear. So as you said, you came the first time, got on the ground, went to the government command center, started to have some meetings with people, and they weren't very receptive. José Andrés: This is great. This is how good my talk was. (Laughter) It's the first talk with a follow-up in the history of TED. I feel so good. (Laughter) NM: So tell us why, what were some of the challenges, and then when you noticed, they started coming to you to ask you. JA: We cannot be asking everything from Red Cross or Salvation Army. But the idea is, I donated before to those organizations, and they are the big organizations, and maybe the problem is that we're expecting too much from them. It's not like they didn't do what they were supposed to do. It's that the perception is that that's what they do. But all of a sudden, you cannot get into a moment like this and wash your hands, and you say somebody else is going to be picking it up. We had a simple problem that had a very simple solution. This was not a faraway country or the Green Zone in Baghdad. This was American soil, a beautiful place called Puerto Rico, with hundreds, thousands of restaurants and people willing to help, but all of a sudden, we had people hungry, and we didn't have a plan how to feed them in the short term. So yes, FEMA, to a degree, was thinking about how to feed the people. Red Cross didn't have the right answers, because Southern Baptist Church, the biggest food organization in America, my heroes, they were never called to Puerto Rico. When you see the Red Cross delivering food in America after a hurricane, it's Southern Baptist Church doing it. We didn't have that in Puerto Rico. Salvation Army came and asked me for 420 meals on a Wednesday rainy night for a local elderly shop. I love to help the Salvation Army, but in my world, they are the ones who are supposed to be helping us to answer those calls of help. Thursday morning is when I wake up super worried that actually we didn't have the plan to feed the island. And some people will say maybe you are making the problem bigger than it was. Well, we had hundreds and hundreds and hundreds and hundreds of organizations knocking on our door, asking for a tray of food, so if that's not proof that the need was real ... We cannot be feeding people in America anymore with MREs or something like you open and, you know, I was giving to this little cat a little bit of those same foods -- (Laughter) and then I gave them the chicken and rice we made, and they went for the chicken and rice. (Laughter) (Applause) They don't even eat that themselves. We can feed humanity for a day or two or five, but those MREs cost, like, 12, 14, 15, 20 dollars to the American taxpayer. It's OK for certain moments, during battle, but not to be feeding Americans for weeks and weeks and weeks, when actually, you can be hiring the local private business community to do the same job better, creating local jobs, helping the local economy to come back, and in the process making sure that everything was going to go back as normal as quick as possible. That's where we began cooking. You were there with me, and that's why we spent every single dollar we had in our credit cards. If AmEx is listening to this, please, a discount would be appreciated. (Laughter) Or Visa. NM: So what's the situation now? You know, it's been a month. You said there's been some improvements in San Juan and focus on the areas outside, but obviously there are still major challenges, and what's next? JA: There are. So what's next is we slowly began going down after, more or less, FEMA let us know that they thought they had everything under control and we were no longer needed, but you only believe everything so much. We moved from the big place you saw, 60,000 meals a day, to another one, as big, but more strategically located, also cheaper, where we are going to be making 20-25,000 meals a day, and then we are leaving four, five, six kitchens strategically located around the island, very high up in the mountains, in the poor areas. We got a lot of data. We know who is using SNAPs, who is using food stamps, the cards. We know who has them and we know who is using them. So in the parts of the island where nobody is using them, those are the parts of the island where we are going to be focusing our efforts. So it's amazing how sometimes simple data can give you a clue of who are the people in need. So we went to a town called Morovis. Beautiful. The best chicken restaurant in the history of mankind. You should all travel to Morovis. DT: Sounds good. JA: So I saw the chicken. We were bringing sandwiches. I stopped. I was with these Homeland Security officers. We ate the chicken. I left to drop these sandwiches in this other place called San Lorenzo. San Lorenzo was critical, because the bridge was broken, and so it was an island inside the island, a little community surrounded by water. Everybody told us, "It's a disaster down there." We dropped the sandwiches. I went back to Morovis, and I thought, you know, if it's a disaster, sandwiches is not enough. I brought 120 chickens, with yucca and with rice, and we went back to that broken bridge, we crossed the river, water up to everywhere. We arrived with the 120 chickens, we dropped the food, and the community were very thankful, but they told us, "We're OK, we don't need more food. We have gas, we have money, we have good food and our water is clean. Take care of the other communities around us that are in more need." You see, communication is key. In these scenarios, we can be relying on fake news or we can be having the real information that we can make smart decisions to really take care of the true issues. That's what we are doing. (Applause) NM: It was an amazing operation, and to witness it firsthand and to play a small role -- JA: You made it happen. NM: At its peak, I think you were up to about 150,000 meals per day, across the island, which is pretty incredible. And I think, at the same time, really sort of setting a model for how this can be done, hopefully, moving forward. I mean, I think that's one of the big learnings out of this -- DT: This is possible. You know, people can replicate this. JA: But I'm going to stop coming to watch TED Talks, because you've got ideas that anything can happen. (Laughter) And then my wife told me, "Man, you told me you were going to cook a thousand meals a day. I cannot leave you alone for a day." (Laughter) But I hope that World Central Kitchen -- you know, one thing we did I didn't say: I picked up the phone and I began calling people, people that I thought had expertise that could help us. So I picked up the phone and I called a company called Bon Appétit, Fedele. Bon Appétit's one of the big catering companies. They do food for Google and for arenas. They're out of California. They belong to a bigger group called Compass. And I told them, "You know what? I need cooks, and I need cooks that can do volume and that can do good, quality volume." In less than 24 hours, I began getting people and chefs. At one point, we got 16 of the best chefs that America can offer. You see, America is an amazing heart country that always is sending their best. What we've been learning over the years is that those chefs of America are going to be playing a role in how we are going to be feeding America and maybe other parts of the world in times of need. What we need to start is bringing the right expertise where the expertise is needed. Sometimes I have a feeling, like with FEMA, we are bringing the wrong expertise in the areas that it's not even needed. The people of FEMA are great people. The men and women are smart, they are prepared, but they live under this amazing hierarchy pyramidal organizational chart that everybody falls out of their own weight. We need to be empowering people to be successful. What we did was a flatter organizational chart where everybody was owning the situation and we all made quick decisions to solve the problems on the spot. (Applause) DT: Absolutely. Another round of applause for José Andrés. (Applause) (Cheering)
À chaque rencontre, nous leur servions à manger, jour après jour. Nous devions nous développer. On a donc déménagé dans un grand stade. De 25 000 repas, on est passé à 50 000. D'un seul coup, nous sommes devenus le plus grand restaurant du monde. On préparait près de 70 000 repas par jour dans un seul endroit. (Applaudissements) Les bénévoles sont venus par centaines. À un certain moment, il y avait plus de 7 000 bénévoles qui travaillaient avec nous pour une heure au moins, et à tout moment, ils étaient plus de 700. Vous voyez, on a créé un mouvement, un mouvement basé sur une idée simple à laquelle tout le monde peut se rallier : nourrissons ceux qui ont faim. En cuisinant des plats que les gens pouvaient reconnaître, pas un machin venu d'un endroit lointain emballé dans du plastique et qui ne sent rien. (Rires) Nous cuisinions des repas qui rappellaient la maison. Dans ces moments-là, les gens ressentent le besoin urgent de se sentir en vie, de savoir que quelqu'un se soucie d'eux. Un repas après l'autre, il s'agissait moins d'apport calorique indispensable pour le corps, que d'une chose plus cruciale pour eux. Ils avaient besoin de savoir que vous, vous, vous, et vous, que vous vous souciez d'eux, que nous leur transmettions le message que nous étions avec eux. Donnez-nous du temps, on essaie de réparer tout ça. Tel était le message que nous découvrions en rejoignant une communauté. Les fruits frais ont commencé à arriver, et même FEMA me demandait : « José, comment fais-tu pour obtenir tous ces aliments ? - C'est simple : je téléphone, je paye et on me les livre. » (Rires) (Applaudissements) On a commencé par San Juan. En moins de temps qu'il ne faut pour le dire, on nourrissait 78 municipalités sur l'île. Un plan était nécessaire. Une seule cuisine ne peut pas nourrir toute l'île. Je suis allé voir FEMA, mais huit gardes m'ont repoussé avec leurs armes. Je leur ai dit que j'avais besoin de 18 cuisines sur l'île. Devinez ! Il y a trois jours, nous avons ouvert la 18ème cuisine aux alentours de Porto Rico. (Applaudissements) Les gens ont enfin pu manger. Les bénévoles ont continué d'affluer. On me disait que nous n'avions pas de système de livraison. Bien sûr que si, nous avions un système. L'île entière de Porto Rico était le système de livraison parfait. Quiconque ayant un camion voulait aider. Quiconque se rendant de A à B nous permettait d'apporter de l'espoir, une assiette et un vrai repas à quelqu'un. On a développé des systèmes incroyables pour les camions-cantines. 10 camions-cantines extraordinaires. Nous avons appris à ne plus utiliser les noms de lieux nécessitant des repas, mais les numéros, les numéros des appartements : Lolo, un ancien combattant de 92 ans, encerclé par l'eau. Nous ne faisions pas qu'offrir de l'espoir aux gens, nous connaissions leur nom, établissant un contact au quotidien, pour nous assurer que les plus âgés ne se sentaient plus seuls dans un moment de désespoir. Nous avons commencé à aller de plus en plus loin, des endroits où, soudainement, tous les ponts étaient détruits. Mais nous devions y aller ; il était trop facile de rester à San Juan. Nous devions atteindre les zones qui nécessitaient le plus notre aide. Alors, on a persévéré, et les gens nous attendaient car ils savaient que nous viendrions, que nous ne les abandonnerions jamais. (Applaudissements) Nos camions-cantines sont devenus nos anges et ils offraient sans cesse de l'espoir. Mais c'était évident : nous devions faire plus. Vieques et Culebra, deux îles éloignées, avaient besoin qu'on les nourrisse. On a fait plus qu'apporter des vivres, installer une cuisine à Vieques et apporter des repas chaque jour à Culebra. Nous avons aussi apporté le premier système de purification d'eau dans l'île de Vieques, où nous ne pouvions filtrer que quatre litres à la minute. Soudain, des problèmes épineux devenaient très simples, avec des solutions faciles. Simplement, en agissant, sans planifier, et sans réunion dans de grands immeubles. (Rires) Nous avons trouvé des moyens créatifs. Besoin d'hélicoptères ? Il n'y a qu'à demander, c'est là. Besoin d'avions ? Il n'y a qu'à demander, payer, c'est là. Sans relâche, nous avons livré des aliments là où c'était nécessaire. Cette idée simple est devenue puissante. Les bénévoles se rendaient dans les îles. Soudain, c'était un mouvement. Les équipes de la cuisine industrielle étaient accueillies par des prières, des chansons, des applaudissements, des câlins, des sourires. Nous avons créé des contacts dans tant d'endroits. Même la garde nationale nous a appelés à l'aide car même nos pauvres gardes de la garde nationale, les héros dans le chaos, ne trouvaient pas un simple repas chaud pour se nourrir. Ensuite, des partenariats se sont mis en place : Mercy Corps, HSI de la Sécurité nationale. Ces partenariats n'ont pas eu besoin de réunions au sommet. Ils se sont mis en place dans un hôtel, au milieu d'une rue, au fin fond de la montagne. C'était évident : en travaillant ensemble, nous pouvions atteindre plus de personnes. Des partenariats qui se nouent logiquement, et l'urgence de l'instant présent est mise au service des gens. Quand on est une organisation humanitaire d'urgence, on ne peut pas planifier de l'aide à fournir dans un mois. Il faut être prêt à offrir son aide à la seconde même où une catastrophe survient. On a nourri les enfants, et soudain, sur toute l'île, encore fragile dans ce moment bien particulier, nous avons vu une ONG comme la nôtre -- nous ne voulions pas être en concurrence avec le secteur privé -- des petits restaurants ont commencé à ouvrir, une certaine normalité, enfin, ce que « normalité » peut signifier aujourd'hui à Porto Rico, est revenue. Alors on a commencé à envoyer le message : Il est temps de quitter les lieux qui sont déjà stabilisés et de nous concentrer sur les zones qui ont toujours besoin d'aide. (Vidéo) : Citoyens de Porto Rico, deux millions de repas ! José Andrès : Bon. Je vous traduis ça. (Rires) 28 jours plus tard, 10 camions-cantines, plus de 7 000 bénévoles, 18 cuisines... Nous avions servi plus de deux millions de repas. (Applaudissements) Vous ici, à TED, vous pouvez être fiers car nous savons que beaucoup d'entre vous font partie du changement. Mais le changement ne survient que si, après avoir quitté cette conférence, nous mettons au service de ceux qui en ont besoin ces idées incroyables, ces sources d'inspiration, et que nous croyons que rien n'est impossible. J'ai débarqué sur une île pour essayer de nourrir les gens. J'ai vu un gros problème. Soudain, les citoyens de Porto Rico ont constaté le même problème que moi, et nous avons fait une seule chose : nous avons cuisiné. Les citoyens de Porto Rico, et les chefs de Porto Rico, dans ces moments de désespoir, ont apporté de l'espoir. Non pas en faisant des réunions, non pas en planifiant, mais avec une idée simple : Cuisinons et nourrissons les gens de Porto Rico. Merci. (Applaudissements) Dave Troy : Reviens ! (Rires) DT : Le public t'adore. (Applaudissements) Nate Mook : Quelques questions rapides, que j'imagine, beaucoup ici aimeraient poser. Donc, tu as expliqué qu'à ton arrivée sur place, tu es allé au centre de commandement du gouvernement, et que tu as rencontré des gens, mais qu'ils n'étaient pas très réceptifs. José Andrés : Super. Ma présentation a été vraiment bonne ! (Rires) C'est la première présentation avec un follow-up chez TED. Ça me fait super plaisir. (Rires) NM : Dis-nous, quels ont été les défis, et quand vous êtes-vous aperçus qu'ils venaient vous demander conseil ? JA : On ne peut pas tout attendre de la Croix Rouge et de l'Armée du Salut. L'idée, c'est que, et j'ai fait des dons à ces organisations dans le passé, ce sont de très grandes organisations, mais le problème est le suivant : nous attendons trop de leur part. Ce n'est pas qu'elles ne réalisent pas ce qu'elles sont supposées faire. C'est la perception que nous avons de ce qu'elles font. Mais dans un moment pareil, on ne peut pas juste s'en laver les mains et penser que quelqu'un d'autre va s'occuper de la situation. Le problème était simple et la solution aussi. On ne parle pas d'un pays éloigné ou de la zone verte de Bagdad. On parle des États-Unis, un lieu magnifique appelé Porto Rico, avec des centaines et des milliers de restaurants et de gens prêts à aider. Mais du jour au lendemain, les gens ont eu faim, et il n'y avait pas de plan en place pour les nourrir à court terme. FEMA réfléchissait, en quelque sorte, à une façon de nourrir les gens. La Croix Rouge n'avait pas les réponses, parce qu'on n'a jamais demandé l'aide de l'Église Baptiste du Sud à Porto Rico, la plus grande banque alimentaire en Amérique, et mes héros à moi. Vous voyez, quand la Croix Rouge livre des aliments après un ouragan en Amérique, c'est l'Église Baptiste du Sud qui le fait. Mais ils n'étaient pas à Porto Rico. L'Armée du Salut est venue nous demander 420 repas un mercredi soir pluvieux, pour un centre de personnes âgées des environs. J'aide l'Armée du Salut avec plaisir, mais dans mon monde, c'est elle qui est censée nous aider à répondre aux appels à l'aide. Jeudi matin, je me suis réveillé très inquiet parce que nous n'avions aucun plan pour nourrir l'île. Certains diront sans doute que nous exagérions le problème. Mais avec des centaines et des centaines d'organisations qui venaient frapper à notre porte pour demander des repas, force est de constater que ce besoin était réel. On ne peut plus nourrir des gens en Amérique avec des portions lyophilisées ou des choses qu'on ouvre. Je donnais ces mêmes boîtes aux petits chats, (Rires) puis je leur ai donné du poulet et du riz que nous avions préparés et ils ont préféré le poulet et le riz. (Rires) (Applaudissements) Même eux ne mangent pas ça. On peut nourrir l'humanité pour un jour ou deux, ou cinq, mais ces rations coûtent 12, 14, 15, 20 dollars aux contribuables américains. Ça convient pour un petit moment, pendant une bataille, mais pas pour nourrir des Américains pendant des semaines entières, alors qu'on pourrait recruter la communauté d'affaires locale pour faire le même travail, mais mieux ; créer des emplois localement, aider l'économie locale à se remettre sur pied, et simultanément, s'assurer que tout va s'arranger et redevenir normal le plus rapidement possible. C'est là que nous avons commencé à cuisiner. Tu étais avec moi, c'est là qu'on a utilisé tout l'argent disponible sur nos cartes de crédit. Si AMEX écoute cette présentation, un petit rabais serait apprécié. (Rires) Visa aussi. NM : Quelle est la situation aujourd'hui ? C'était il y a un mois. Tu as dit que la situation s'est améliorée à San Juan, et que tu te concentres sur la campagne. Mais il reste sans aucun doute des défis majeurs. C'est quoi la suite ? JA : La suite, c'est que nous allons progressivement nous retirer, après que FEMA nous ait plus ou moins fait comprendre qu'ils pensaient avoir tout sous contrôle, et que nos services n'étaient plus nécessaires, mais bon, on ne les croit pas vraiment. Nous avons quitté le stade, 60 000 repas par jour, pour emménager dans un autre espace, aussi grand, mais localisé stratégiquement et moins cher. Là, on va préparer 20 à 25 000 repas par jour. Ensuite, on va laisser quatre, cinq ou six cuisines dans des endroits stratégiques de l'île, loin dans les montagnes, dans les régions pauvres. On a beaucoup de données. Nous savons qui utilise l'assistance alimentaire, des coupons, des cartes. Nous savons qui les possède et qui les utilise. Dans les zones de l'île où personne ne les utilise, c'est là que nous allons concentrer nos efforts. C'est incroyable comme de simples données peuvent fournir des indices sur les gens dans le besoin. Nous nous sommes rendus dans une petite ville appelée Morovis. Très belle. La meilleure rôtisserie dans l'histoire de l'humanité. Vous devriez visiter Morovis. DT : C'est une bonne idée. JA : On avait des sandwichs. Mais avec les gens de la sécurité nationale, on s'y est arrêté et on y a mangé du poulet rôti. J'ai apporté les sandwichs dans une autre ville, San Lorenzo. La situation y était critique car le pont était détruit. C'était une île dans l'île, une petite communauté entourée par l'eau. Tout le monde nous parlait du désastre là-bas. On a apporté les sandwichs. Mais sur le retour vers Morovis, j'ai pensé que si c'est une catastrophe, les sandwichs ne suffiront pas. J'ai apporté 120 poulets, avec du yucca et du riz, et une fois arrivés au pont détruit, on a traversé le fleuve. Il y avait de l'eau partout. Mais nous avons apporté les 120 poulets, et la nourriture. La communauté nous a remerciés puis nous a dit ceci : « Ça va aller. Nous n'avons plus besoin de nourriture. On a le gaz, de l'argent, de la nourriture et notre eau est pure. Aidez les autres communautés qui en ont plus besoin. » La communication est la clé. Dans ces scénarios, on peut soit se baser sur des données erronées, soit obtenir les bonnes informations pour prendre des décisions intelligentes et vraiment s'occuper des vrais problèmes. C'est ce que nous faisons. (Applaudissements) NM : C'est une opération incroyable, et la chance de pouvoir l'observer, d'y contribuer un tout petit peu -- JA : Tu l'as lancée. NM : Au moment le plus intense, vous prépariez 150 000 repas par jour, dans toute l'île. C'est incroyable. Je crois que vous avez aussi mis sur pied un modèle pour réaliser cela ; espérons qu'il sera utile dans l'avenir. C'est une des grandes leçons de cette histoire -- DT : C'est possible. On peut répliquer cela. JA : Mais je ne vais plus regarder TED, car vous avez cette conviction que tout est possible. (Rires) Ma femme m'a dit ceci : « Tu m'as dit que tu allais cuisiner 1 000 repas par jour. Je ne peux pas te laisser seul, même pour une journée ! » (Rires) J'espère que World Central Kitchen -- il y a une chose que j'ai omis de dire : j'ai pris mon téléphone et j'ai contacté plein de gens qui avaient selon moi une expertise utile pour nous. J'ai donc téléphoné à une entreprise appelée Bon Appétit, à Fedele. C'est l'une des grandes entreprises de service traiteur. Ils travaillent pour Google et les grands stades. Ils viennent de Californie et appartiennent à un groupe plus grand, Compass. Je leur ai dit ceci : « J'ai besoin de cuisiniers, de cuisiniers capables de faire du volume, mais du volume bon et de qualité. » En moins de 24 heures, j'ai commencé à réunir les gens et les chefs. À un moment, nous avions les 16 meilleurs chefs d'Amérique. L'Amérique est un pays avec un cœur extraordinaire, qui envoie toujours ses meilleurs éléments. Ce que nous avons appris avec les années, c'est que ces chefs américains vont jouer un rôle dans la manière avec laquelle on nourrit l'Amérique, et peut-être d'autres parties du monde, dans les situations d'urgence. Ce que nous devons lancer, c'est l'apport d'expertise adéquate là où elle est nécessaire. Parfois j'ai le sentiment, comme avec FEMA, qu'on rassemble la mauvaise expertise là où elle n'est même pas nécessaire. Les gens de FEMA sont des gens fabuleux. Des hommes et des femmes intelligents et préparés, mais sous une incroyable arborescence organisationnelle hiérarchique en pyramide où tout le monde est écrasé par le poids de la hiérarchie. Il convient d'émanciper les gens pour atteindre le succès. Nous avons une organisation plus aplatie, où chaque personne s'approprie la situation, et prend des décisions pour résoudre les problèmes quand ils surgissent. (Applaudissements) DT : Exactement. Applaudissez encore une fois José Andrés. (Applaudissements) (Encouragements)